[Music]
hi everyone it's dr a and in this video
we're going to discuss a process
of bone growth and development called
intramembranous ossification
the first thing that i'd like to share
with you is that bone is a type of
replacement tissue
in other words bone tissue develops to
replace an existing tissue
and that existing tissue is known as
cartilage so we can think about
cartilage as a blueprint for the
building of bone tissue
so in this process we start with unique
specialized cells called mesenchymal
cells
and this type of cell is a precursor
cell for connective tissue
in other words it's this cell that leads
to the development of a variety of
connective tissues
and for the purposes of this video we're
going to utilize a green circle
to represent the mesenchymal cell
and it's through intramembranous
ossification
that we have the development of flat
bones like those of the skull
the ribs and the clavicle
so ultimately this process begins with
the embryonic skeleton and remember that
here we're starting with the cartilage
model
and in the cartilage we begin with
mesenchymal cells which gather together
these mesenchymal cells then
differentiate into specific connective
tissues
some of these differentiate into
capillaries and others become osteogenic
cells
and for note-taking purposes osteogenic
cells are the precursor cells meaning
that they ultimately become bone cells
now these osteogenic cells differentiate
and become osteoblast
and these osteoblasts appear as a
cluster of cells
and this cluster of cells is called or
referred to as an ossification center
these osteoblasts then secrete an
unmineralized material called osteoid
and although not pictured once this
osteoid is secreted it allows for the
deposit of collagen fibers into the
osteoid
and following this
we'll soon have the deposit of minerals
such as calcium and phosphorus which
allow the tissue to begin heartening
over the course of a few days
and through this process the
become entrapped in the surrounding
tissue
now what's unique to this process is
that in the areas where osteoid is
secreted around the capillaries it
becomes what we call trabecular bone
and as this process continues we'll end
up having two distinct portions
the outer portion of this bony tissue is
called the periosteum or compact bone
and again the inner portion which is
largely surrounded by capillaries is
referred to as trabecular bone
and this is the process of
intramembranous ossification in a
nutshell
well thank you for watching this video i
hope it's been helpful and if you indeed
found value in it please like comment
share and subscribe i'll look forward to
seeing you in the next video
you